Guide to the Arthur Williams Wright Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Arthur Williams Wright papers
1755-1876
MS 1860
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
0.75
The papers consist of materials written and/or collected by Arthur Williams Wright, primarily his writings and notes on scientific topics, such as meteorite analysis.
Wright, Arthur W. (Arthur Williams), 1836-1915
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Barbara Hoblitzelle Newell, 2005.
Associated Materials
Natural Sciences Manuscript Collection (MS 583), Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library.
Biographical / Historical
Arthur Williams Wright was born on September 8, 1836, in Lebanon, Connecticut. He received his Yale College B.A in 1859 and his Ph.D. in 1861, the year Yale became the first American university to award this degree. He served as a Yale College tutor in Latin from 1863 to 1866 and in natural philosophy from 1866 to 1868. Wright was an instructor in physics from 1867 to 1868. He furthered his studies with a year at Heidelberg and Berlin. In 1871, he was appointed professor of molecular physics and chemistry at Yale, and in 1878, professor of experimental physics, a position he held until his retirement in 1906. In addition to his academic appointments, Wright was a consultant to the U. S. Signal Service, 1881-1886; the Annual Assay Commission in 1887; and a member of the party sent out by the United States Naval Observatory in the summer of 1878 to observe the total eclipse of the sun. In 1876, he observed for the first time the occurrence of gases in stony meteorites, analyzed them as those of iron meteorites, and investigated their spectra and the relation of these to the spectra of comets. Following the discovery of X-rays in 1895, he was the first American to obtain results from using X-rays. Wright was married to Susan Forbes Silliman. He died in New Haven on December 19, 1915. The Arthur W. Wright Nuclear Structure Laboratory on the Yale campus is named for him.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of materials written and/or collected by Arthur Williams Wright, primarily his writings and notes on scientific topics, such as meteorite analysis.
Arrangement
The papers are arranged by type of material.
Conditions Governing Access
Due to the physical nature of the letterbook in box 2, staff supervision is required.
The materials are open for research.
Wright, Arthur W. (Arthur Williams), 1836-1915; Yale University -- Faculty; Yale University. Physics Department
- Inventory, 1755-1876, undated
  - Diaries
    - [Lyon, William?], Journey to Quebec, 1823 May 20-August 7 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - [unknown author], French and Indian War, 1755-1761 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Memorabilia
    - Map of the Hudson River, 1829 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Miscellaneous loose pages, 1817, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Writings
    - "Benjamin Silliman, Professor of Chemistry, Pharmacy, Mineralogy, and Geology" [notes and printed document], undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Geometric problems [journal and loose pages], undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - "Images produced by lightning", [187?] (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - "The Laboratory" [printed document], undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Meteorite analysis [notes], [1875?] December 18-[1876?] February 29, undated (Box 1, Folder 9 - 18)
    - Miscellaneous notes, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - "On the Gases contained in Meteorites", 1876 March 18 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - "On the Polarization of the Zodiacal Light", 1874 April 6 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - "On the Spectrum of the Zodiacal Light", 1874 June 5 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - "Solutions of Problems proposed July, 1857" (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Letterbook of G. & D. Cook & Co. [carriage company?], 1861-1862 (Box 2)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Due to the physical nature of the letterbook, staff supervision is required.